- Do you travel with a laptop? - My laptop has been dead for about six years. I don't know where the charger is. - We can help you with - That.
ノートパソコン、旅に持っていく？ 僕のパソコン、6年くらい死んでる。充電器がどこかも分からない。それなら手伝えるよ。それ。
I know. We met for the first time in Rome on a small street. - Yes. - You were playing in Rome that week with the smile. Yeah.
知ってる。初めて会ったの、ローマの細い道だった。うん。その週、The Smileでローマに出てた。うん。
So I'd just been talking about... I was going to that show. Was it before the show? It was before the show. Yeah.
だからちょうど話してたんだ。あのショーに行くって。ショーの前？ 前だった。うん。
And a friend of mine had asked me if we'd ever met and I had said that we hadn't.
友達に、会ったことある？って聞かれて、ない、って言ってた。
So I was walking down the street and I noticed you because you were wearing a hat that said acid on it. And I thought, "Oh, that's a cool hat."
道を歩いてたら君に気づいた。アシッドって帽子をかぶってたから。いい帽子だな、って。
And I was like, "That guy's wearing a cool hat." And then I was like, "Oh, it's you." And then I had Moonshape Pool playing in my headphones and I stopped it and was like, "Oh, hello."
いい帽子の人だな、って。それから、あ、君だ、って。ヘッドフォンで『A Moon Shaped Pool』がかかってて、止めて、やあ、って。
- Mr. York. - Mr. York. - Hello. I was impressed. - And you said, "Oh, hi." And then - - No, I said, "What the fuck?"
ヨークさん。ヨークさん。こんにちは。感心したよ。君は「やあ」って。いや、僕は「なんだよ」って言った。
- Yeah. And - Then - Are you doing standing in the street? - And then I came to the show and then we met kind of properly at the show.
うん。それで、道に立って何してるの？ それからショーに行って、ショーでちゃんと会った。
- Yeah. I didn't know you were living in Rome a lot. I had no idea. So I was double confused.
うん。ローマにそんなに住んでるなんて知らなかった。全然。だから二重に混乱した。
- Yeah, it was really like, I think for me, through that and then the show, it always been, you to me had always been that person I was kind of scared of meeting.
うん、本当に。僕には、あのこととショーを通して、君はずっと、会うのがちょっと怖い人だった。
- Oh yeah, I've got a whole list. - Yeah, totally. And I remember feeling so light afterwards, I think of just, oh, people and they're kind and they're nice.
ああ、僕にもリストがある。うん、まったく。あとですごく軽くなったのを覚えてる。人って優しくて、いい人なんだ、って。
And it was very nice. - I was also impressed that you were just walking down the street. I was like, where's this security?
すごくよかった。君がただ道を歩いてるのも感心した。警備はどこ、って。
Because I mean, I know I can do it. I didn't know you could do it. Is that a choice?
僕はできるって分かってる。君ができるとは知らなかった。それ、選んでるの？
- In the early days when I was in the band and stuff, so much of the hotel experience felt very locked in.
バンドの初期とか、ホテルはすごく閉じ込められてた。
It felt like there was this like, oh, it's not safe for me to be out in some way. Yeah, that - Makes sense.
外に出るのは、なんか安全じゃない、みたいな感じ。うん、それは分かる。
- And then I remember I had a girlfriend who was very outgoing and she was coming to London and I was kind of like, oh
それから、すごく外向的な彼女がロンドンに来ることになって、
if we just sit in my house for three days, she's going to think I'm nuts. So we kind of walked everywhere and it was this realization for me of like, oh, it's fine to be outside.
家に3日いたら、僕がおかしいと思われる、って。だからどこでも歩いた。外にいていいんだ、って気づいた。
It kind of broke that thing. And then now it's changed my life in such a big way. It's like how you stay connected to the world and the experience.
それが壊れた。今は人生がすごく変わった。世界や経験と、つながり続ける方法みたいに。
And I read something about walking being the artist's kind of perspective because you're at ground level and you see things that you just don't see if you're driving - Everywhere.
歩くのはアーティストの視点だ、って読んだ。地面の高さにいるから、車だと見えないものが見える。どこでも。
It's also a good way to write. I wrote Wolf at the Door. I was going through a really bad moment and I walked for like two and a half days, rain, didn't matter.
書くのにもいい。『Wolf at the Door』はそう書いた。すごく悪い時期で、2日半くらい歩いた。雨でも関係なく。
A notebook in my hand and just wrote all and I felt so much better at the end of it. But also it's not just the walking, it's the walking past people.
ノートを手に、全部書いた。終わりにはすごく楽になった。でも歩くだけじゃない。人の横を通り過ぎること。
The simple thing of people watching, playing that game of imagining as someone walks by where they're going, what they're doing, all that stuff brings you out of yourself
人を見る、あの単純なこと。通り過ぎる人がどこへ行くか、何をしてるか想像する。それが自分の外に出してくれる。
brings you out of your troubles. I mean, without it, See, it's really easy to get lost without being able to do that.
悩みの外へ。それがないと、本当に迷子になりやすい。
I guess I had a similar thing, but it happened for you very young, happened for me later. But I remember when we were on tour with REM and Michael Stipe figuring out that...
似たことはあった。君はすごく若いときに起きて、僕はあとだった。REMのツアーで、マイケル・スタイプが気づいた。
I mean, well, it was kind of obvious because when we played, I would just hide in the dressing room before them and never went out anywhere or whatever.
Obviousだった。僕らが出るとき、僕は彼らの前、楽屋に隠れて、どこにも出なかった。
So he started dragging me out and he gave me this trick. He said, "If you don't care, they don't care. If you're not looking, they're not looking."
だから引っ張り出されて、技をもらった。気にしなきゃ、向こうも気にしない。見てなきゃ、見られない、って。
And it works. I remember being in Stockholm going to some really busy club and he said, "Try it." And it works and nobody bothered us. So there are moments when you will feel vulnerable.
効くんだ。ストックホルムの、すごく混んだクラブで「やってみろ」って。効いて、誰も構ってこなかった。傷つきやすい瞬間はある。
There are moments when shit will happen or the sun will be printing your picture one too many times and you'll not want it or something. And I've had that.
ひどいことが起きる瞬間もある。写真を刷られすぎて、もう嫌になるとか。僕もあった。
It's not an easy decision to make, but it's better than the alternative.
簡単な決断じゃない。でも、もう一方よりはいい。
The alternative, I know people who got death threats and then wouldn't leave the house and had security patrolling their house to hold all that sort of stuff.
もう一方は、殺害予告を受けて家から出られなくなって、警備が家を巡回する。そういうの全部。
You don't want that. I think if you have something that's very successful, there's a lot of pressure to repeat that, which I'm sure you'll probably feel or you do feel sometimes.
それは嫌だ。すごく当たったものがあると、それを繰り返せ、って圧力が大きい。君も感じるだろうし、ときどき感じてると思う。
It doesn't sort of go anywhere because that's like working to commission. You know what I mean? It's like we like those. Let's paint that - Again. - Yeah.
それはどこにも行かない。注文仕事みたいだから。分かる？ あれが好きだった。もう一回それを描いて。うん。
Could you do that? I remember some movies, some being drawn in to watch some clip of the movie, "We'd really like you to do something like this."
できる？ 映画の一部を見せられて、こういうのをやってほしい、って引き込まれるのを覚えてる。
And I was like, "Use that." That sort of mentality of like, "We want your name at the top, but we'd like you to repeat yourself, but
それを使え、って。名前は一番上に欲しい。でも自分を繰り返してほしい。
we don't want to ask you to repeat yourself because we know it's rude. So we're kind of thinking about it's commercial art form, so therefore you're always going to get people asking you to do that."
繰り返せとは言いたくない。失礼だと分かってるから。商業のアートだから、いつもそう頼まれる、って考えてる。
- It's an interesting cycle, I think, because you make something that I think connects with people because they find something in it that you've captured something about the human experience, whether it's a
面白い循環だと思う。人とつながるものを作る。人がその中に、人間の経験の何かを見つけるから。
vulnerability or a sensitivity that comes with being human. And then I think any kind of success around that thing makes it take on this life of its own.
弱さとか、人間でいることの繊細さ。それから成功が、それに勝手な命を与える。
Then everything around you kind of makes your experience incredibly not human and then moving - - Yes, artificial. - Yeah.
周りの全部が、経験をものすごく人間じゃなくする。それから動いていく。うん、作り物。うん。
And then it feels like the kind of goal is to how do you shut that out when you're making stuff so that you can still be making stuff about the human experience.
ものを作るとき、それをどう遮って、まだ人間の経験について作れるか、が目標みたいになる。
I've always thought if I was to make music about being in a studio and touring and all of the kind of shiny things that come with that and how wonderful that is -
スタジオやツアーや、ついてくるキラキラについて音楽を作ったら、っていつも思ってた。それがどれだけ素晴らしいか。
It's - Shiny for you, mate. It's - Not shiny very well. It's definitely not interesting to me, so it can't possibly be interesting to anyone else.
君にはキラキラだよ。あんまりキラキラしてない。僕には全然面白くない。だから他の人にも面白いはずがない。
What I love about your work, for example, is for so many people who look at you in this way of in this kind of godlike status in terms of a creative - And
君の仕事が好きなのは、たくさんの人が、創造の神みたいに君を見てるのに。そして
- An artist to still be someone who kind of looks at, oh, this is the gritty part of life.
アーティストなのに、まだ、これが人生のざらついた部分だ、って見てる人でいること。
I think that's what's so impressive about so much of your work is that for people to revere you in such a way - And to - Still be looking at what's under the
それがすごいところだと思う。あんなに崇められて、まだ爪の下を見てる。
fingernails rather than... - All I can think is I think the reason for that was it's as much having to learn quite a difficult lesson.
爪の下を。それより上じゃなくて。思えるのは、かなり難しい教訓を学ばなきゃいけなかったからだ、ってこと。
And if you have to do lots of interviews, for example, if you end up having to explain your work in a particular way, when people are like...
インタビューをたくさんやらなきゃ、仕事を決まった説明の仕方で説明することになる。人が…
You can get picked apart and what you've done can get picked apart in a way, which is what you mean by artificial, I think really, in a way that's not necessary.
ばらされる。やったことが、ある意味ばらされる。それが君の言う作り物だと思う。必要ない形で。
I mean, it used to be a lot worse. Now I guess it's not as bad, but around kiddo amnesia, before that, I really struggled.
昔の方がずっと悪かった。今はそこまでじゃない。でもKid Aのあたり、その前は本当に苦しかった。
Every time I had to try to do something new, I was explaining it to myself while I was doing it, literally. It's like a form of madness and I couldn't get out of it.
新しいことをやるたびに、やりながら自分に説明してた。文字通り。狂気の一種で、抜けられなかった。
The experience of trying to make music, even the experience of being in the studio or listening back to stuff became this really weird hollow thing because I felt I needed to justify it
音楽を作ること、スタジオにいること、聴き返すことまで、変な空洞になった。正当化しなきゃ、って感じたから。
somehow, but not justify it in a sort of apologize, justify it in a kind of intellectual way. And the reason for that was I needed to get out of it.
謝る正当化じゃなくて、頭で正当化する。理由は、そこから出なきゃいけなかったから。
I needed to just get out of the studio and I needed to just walk. A lot of that was down to the fact that nobody cares, man.
スタジオを出て、ただ歩かなきゃ。多くは、誰も気にしてない、ってことだった。
Nobody cares that it's difficult. And so if you're worried, if you're bummed out that it's difficult, fucking stop, go and do something else.
誰も、難しいことなんて気にしない。難しいって落ち込んでるなら、やめろ。他のことをしろ。
Also, later on as you have kids and all this kind of thing, the choice to carry on doing this kind of work, you have to enjoy it.
子どもができたりすると、この仕事を続けるには、楽しさが要る。
And the enjoyment comes from having to start again from scratch every time you start again, whatever you learn, you've got to unlearn or all this kind of nonsense.
楽しさは、始めるたびにゼロからやり直すことから来る。学んだことは、学び直さなきゃいけない。そういう話。
Also, songwriting is a very odd... I mean, going to the Ivan Novellos thing, I mean, I don't hang out with songwriters, but apparently I am one. And you realize that actually songwriting is quite a naive thing.
曲作りはすごく変で。アイヴァー・ノヴェロの話に行くと、ソングライターとはつるまない。でもどうやら僕はそうらしい。曲作りは、かなり無邪気なことだと分かる。
It's like you can't be savvy about it. You can work really hard on it, but the good stuff just happens and you don't know why.
抜け目なくはできない。すごく働ける。でもいいものは、ただ起きる。なぜか分からない。
And you've got to be honest with yourself that you don't know why, and you've got to carry on being honest with yourself that you don't know why.
なぜか分からない、って自分に正直でいなきゃ。分からないまま、正直でい続けなきゃ。
And when stuff forms that you like, you just grab onto it and you don't let it go because the stuff you like is you don't know why you like it.
好きな形ができたら、掴んで離さない。好きなものは、なぜ好きか分からないから。
Why would Pyramid Song... I mean, it's three chords over and over again and the same lyric. How does that make sense?
なぜ『Pyramid Song』が。コード3つを繰り返して、歌詞も同じ。なんで成立するんだ？
That kind of thing. But you like it, you like it. You're not bothered about if anyone else likes it.
そういうこと。でも好きなんだ。好きなんだ。他の人が好きかどうかは気にしない。
- I've always wondered if part of that is why the idea of imposter syndrome that can come with commercial success exists is I think if you write in that way
ずっと不思議だった。商業的な成功についてくる、偽物みたいな感じの一部は、そういう書き方だからじゃないか、って。
there's a part of you that kind of acknowledges... It almost feels like you're not responsible for it.
一部は認めてる。自分が責任を持ってないみたいに感じる。
So then if people are like, "Oh, you've made this thing and that means that you're this," there's something in there that feels like, "Oh, I can't take credit for it.
人が「これを作った、だから君はこれだ」って言うと、功績は受け取れない、って感じがある。
It just kind of happened to me."
ただ、僕に起きただけ、って。
I think I've always found the things that I end up liking the most or have been the most special things to me are the ones where you kind of write it and then
いちばん好きになるもの、いちばん特別なものは、書いてから、
as you're listening back or reading lyrics back, you're kind of learning something about yourself of you're realizing that you've said something rather than I'm going to sit down, I'm going to say this.
聴き返したり歌詞を読み返したりして、自分について何かを学んでるものだ。これを言おう、と座って言うんじゃなくて、言ってしまったことに気づく。
Yeah. - And you might not realize and you might record it and track it and everything and not realize until you've mastered it. Yeah. And then you suddenly hear, "Oh shit, that's what I - Meant."
うん。気づかないこともある。録って、全部やって、マスタリングするまで気づかない。うん。それから「くそ、これが言いたかったことだ」って。
Yeah. - Yeah, that's right. I think, but at the same time, it's not not you because you spend... It's not divine intervention or anything like that. It's like you got to show up.
うん。うん、その通り。でも同時に、君じゃないわけじゃない。時間をかけてるから。神が降りてくるとかじゃない。出てこなきゃいけない。
In order to find these things, you have to show up. Much like with any job, you develop skills at what you do. If you're a cameraman, you develop skills, you develop a relationship with your camera.
見つけるには、出てこなきゃ。どんな仕事でも同じ。腕がつく。カメラマンなら、カメラとの関係ができる。
If you are a songwriter, you develop a relationship with whatever the hell that is.
ソングライターなら、それが何であれ、それとの関係ができる。
You have to learn to accept the months of imposter syndrome where you're like, "I don't have anything to justify all this amazing equipment in my studio. I can't find anything I like.
偽物みたいな感じの何ヶ月かを受け入れなきゃ。スタジオのすごい機材を正当化するものが何もない。好きなものが見つからない。
That's okay." And then you'll pick up your notebook or whatever and there'll be one line in it that sets you off. But the point is you showed up because it's really easy not to show up.
それでいい。ノートを拾うと、一行があって、それが火をつける。要点は、出てきたこと。出てこないのは本当に簡単だから。
It's really easy to go, "Oh, I'll get to that one. Oh, I know what I'm doing. It's fine." Because it's the small acts that end up being the big acts.
あとでやる、何をしてるか分かってる、大丈夫、は簡単。小さいことが、大きいことになるから。
It's really easy to get into this kind of mentality that everything is a performance where it's not everything is searching, in fact, and searching for stuff that speaks to you, not anybody else.
全部がパフォーマンスだ、って考えに入りやすい。実際は全部が探すこと。自分に話しかけるものを探す。他の誰かじゃない。
- Someone wants to describe it to me as kind of like surfing where you can practice getting up on the board and the waves are kind of going and sometimes you'll be practicing,
誰かがサーフィンに例えた。ボードに立つ練習はできる。波は来てる。ときどき練習してても、
but there's no waves. And then if a wave comes but you haven't practiced enough, you're not going to be able to surf it. That's right.
波がない。波が来ても、練習が足りないと乗れない。その通り。
And - Then - When they kind of happen, it's like the combination of you've practiced being able to capture it and it's something is happening at the right time.
それが起きるときは、掴む練習をしてきて、正しいタイミングで何かが起きてる。
- Yeah, you're ready when it's... Yeah. - And that's when it's like - - Or if I'm surfing, you're not ready ever or you're on the rock scope.
うん、準備ができてるとき。うん。それが、みたいな。僕がサーフィンしてたら、いつまでも準備できないか、岩の上にいる。
Just - Like being open. And I think I used to feel really... I've had a big shift away from... I think I used to feel really labor focused about art in general.
ただ開いてること。昔はアートを、労働で測ってた。大きな変化があった。
If it was walking in and seeing a painting and doing that like, "Oh, that can't have taken more than 10 minutes or whatever."
絵を見て、これ、10分もかかってないだろ、みたいな。
And I felt like to justify it, I had to be in the studio for months at a time and just in there. - That's your imposter syndrome speaking.
正当化するには、何ヶ月もスタジオにいなきゃ、って感じた。ただそこに。それは偽物みたいな声が話してる。
Yeah. Because that's how... I'm the same. Yeah.
うん。そういうことだから。僕も同じ。うん。
I mean, sometimes it's fun, but sometimes you're like you're doing it because you feel you should do it because you need to stay ahead of the game or you need to keep proving
楽しいときもある。でも、やるべきだからやってるときがある。先を行かなきゃ、とか、
that you are who you say you are.
自分が言う自分だって証明し続けなきゃ、って。
I mean, there are good sides to it, but there's a point where it just doesn't give you anything back and it can really freak you out because you've been there for weeks and
いい面もある。でも何も返ってこなくなる点がある。何週間もいて、
nothing's happening. That's when you rely on other people. Yeah. I mean, I don't know about you, but I don't really get much done if I'm in the studio on my own.
何も起きないと、本当に怖くなる。そのとき他の人に頼る。うん。君はどうか分からない。一人だと、あまり進まない。
I get stuff done super quick when I've got someone in front of me to show it to. - I'm - Like, running around, trying to find my notes, trying to...
目の前に見せる人がいると、すごく早く終わる。走り回って、ノートを探して。
It could be this, it could be this, it could be this. But if I'm on my own. Yeah.
これかもしれない、これかもしれない。一人だと。うん。
- I feel like it's a real line to ride with that because I still feel like I get it on stage sometimes where I think the kind of sweet spot is where you're
そこは本当に綱渡りだ。ステージでもまだある。いい場所は、
relaxed in that kind of flow state where it feels like, "Oh, this feels really easy. It feels like it's just happening and this is great." And then I kind of click over to like, "Oh, it feels too easy.
流れに乗ってて、これ、すごく簡単。ただ起きてる。最高、って感じるところ。それから、簡単すぎる。
Am I not working hard enough?" - You mean on stage? - Yeah. Okay.
頑張ってないんじゃないか、に切り替わる。ステージで？ うん。分かった。
It's like when it feels most natural is when I think the show is at its best, but then I have this voice of like, it shouldn't - Be the same.
いちばん自然なときが、ショーがいちばんいいときだと思う。でも声がある。同じであるべきじゃない、って。
Actors have the same thing, right? When you're acting... The joke with Radiohead is always like we'll have moments in the show where like, "Oh my God, we're so great."
役者も同じだよね。レディオヘッドのジョークは、ショーの途中で「神様、僕ら最高」ってなると、
And exactly that moment, someone fucks up every time without fail. We all look around going off. - Yeah. How do you find the...
まさにその瞬間、誰かが必ずミスる。見回して、ずれてる。うん。どうやって。
I guess in the studio mostly how different is it for you in terms of how much do you enjoy the kind of pros and cons of when you're making music with the band
スタジオでは特に、バンドで作るときと、一人で作るとき、楽しさはどれくらい違う？
versus making stuff by yourself? Do you like the kind of what the friction can make in that scenario or do you tend to enjoy like, "Oh, I'm going to have this idea and actually I get to just...
その摩擦が生むものが好き？ それとも、このアイデアを最後まで自分で見られる、が好き？
I'm going to just see this all the way through." - It wasn't until after kid A, I remember quietly saying to Nijah, "I've got all these things.
Kid Aのあとまでだった。ナイジェルに静かに言った。「こういうものが全部ある。
I just want to do them on my own. It doesn't make sense to try and include anybody else." Up until that point, it was just a really alien concept.
一人でやりたい。他の人を入れる意味がない」。それまでは、本当に異質な考えだった。
We've known each other a mind boggling number of years now. We all know each other's musical strengths and musical weaknesses. So you're spending a lot of the time working around that.
気の遠くなる年数、知り合いだ。強みと弱みは、みんな知ってる。だからその周りを回って働く時間が多い。
I mean, we haven't worked, we haven't been in the studio together for a long time, so I don't know how it would actually feel now. The upside of that is you get this sort of...
長いこと、一緒にスタジオにいない。今はどう感じるか分からない。いい面は、
It has to go through all these different filters and all these different perspectives and all these different kind of tastes.
いろんなフィルター、いろんな視点、いろんな好みを通らなきゃいけない。
And because of that, it strengthens it because the point is that whatever the idea is, if it survives all this, it becomes so much bigger than the sum of its parts.
そのせいで強くなる。アイデアが全部を生き延びたら、部分を足したよりずっと大きくなる。
When you work on your own, it's much harder to get that.
一人だと、それを得るのはずっと難しい。
It's also like the relationships you develop with the people you work with and you write with are weird relationships because sometimes this person contributes, sometimes this person contributes.
一緒に働く人、一緒に書く人との関係も変だ。この人が出すとき、あの人が出すときがある。
Sometimes it's what happens in the studio and Nigel's making shit happen. It's all these different things. I don't know how to answer that. I know that when I work on my own, it's quick because it's just me.
スタジオで起きること。ナイジェルが何かを起こしてる。いろんなもの。答え方が分からない。一人だと早い。僕だけだから。
I mean, with the smile again, it's totally different because Johnny just generates ideas all the time. Skinner works faster than any human being I've ever met and can respond to literally, as you probably know, anything.
The Smileはまた全然違う。ジョニーはいつもアイデアを出す。スキナーは、会った誰より速い。君も知ってると思うけど、何にでも反応できる。
You throw it at him and I'm in the middle going, "All right, well why don't you guys record this because I don't understand what's going on and I'll go away and think about it.
投げると、真ん中で「分かった、君たち録って。何が起きてるか分からない。考えてくる」。
Or I'll try get in the middle of it and I don't know what's happening. I'm lost."
あるいは真ん中に入ろうとして、何が起きてるか分からない。迷子だ。
My favorite experiences in the studio is I like when someone's playing something that's good and I don't understand why it's good and I pick up a mic and respond to it and then
スタジオでいちばん好きなのは、誰かがいいものを弾いてて、なぜいいか分からないとき。マイクを持って反応して、
I will listen back to it like you're saying, like I'm trying to explain about despite yourself. I have no idea who that was or Is that us?
聴き返す。君が言ってたみたいに、自分に反して。あれは誰だったんだ。僕らか？
Yeah, that's us. That thing, that's the best bit. - Yeah. - And that's when you have... You only get that when you have other people. You never get that just with yourself.
うん、僕らだ。あれがいちばんいい。うん。それは他の人がいるときだけ。自分だけじゃ起きない。
- Do you find it when it comes to releasing stuff and in the making it process
出すとき、作ってる過程で、
do you find it more vulnerable to be working and putting out your own stuff where although it's so much of you for it to be like it's just me and there's no...
自分のものを出す方が、傷つきやすい？ こんなに自分なのに、僕だけで、誰も。
Someone says, "Oh, I don't like this," that was Johnny's idea. It's fine. No, I get that. Is there any more vulnerable - For you to - No, I don't get that.
これは好きじゃない、って言われたら、ジョニーのアイデアだった、で済む。分かる。それより傷つきやすい？ いや、それは分からない。
I mean, it's all vulnerable. Yeah. I mean, but at the same time, I don't know about you, but
全部傷つきやすい。うん。でも同時に、君はどうか分からない。
if I'm finishing a record, if I can't sit down and listen to it and be comfortable with it and happy with it, it's not going out. So the vulnerable bit happens - - When you're writing it.
レコードを仕上げるとき、座って聴いて、落ち着いて、幸せじゃなきゃ出さない。傷つきやすいのは、書いてるとき。
- Yeah. When you're trying to finish the fucking lyrics, that's when it's the worst. Words, right? How do you do words?
うん。歌詞を終わらせようとしてるときが、いちばん最悪。言葉だよね。言葉、どうやってる？
- I've never found the one method. It's never been like I write a poem and then I put it to music or I write this and then I do it this way.
一つの方法は見つけたことがない。詩を書いてから曲にする、とか、これを書いてからこうする、は一度もなかった。
I think what is so exciting to me about doing it is so often the good stuff tends to come from a few weeks or a couple months or whatever of like, "Oh
興奮するのは、いいものが、何週間も「何もない。何も持ってない」から来ることが多いから。
I've got nothing. I don't have anything." It's - All - Gone. Yeah, - I understand. And then - All of a sudden you write something and you're like, "I really like this.
全部、なくなった。うん、分かる。それから急に何か書いて、これ、本当に好き。
I don't know why." And when that comes in lots of different ways, if it's like I have a line or I have a piano thing or something that you just like or a melody that's mumbled over
なぜか分からない。それがいろんな形で来る。一行、ピアノ、好きなもの、何かの上でつぶやくメロディ。
something, usually there's a word in it. Yeah. And then it's a lot of like, "Oh, I'm building a song around these three words that sound great over this thing."
たいてい、その中に言葉がある。うん。それから、この3語がこの上ですごくいい。この周りに曲を建ててる。
And you're like - - That is the correct process. - Yeah. - Yeah. In my opinion. If you got a few words that hang everything off and you don't understand why, then that's the most exciting
それが正しいプロセスだ。うん。うん。僕の意見では。全部をぶら下げる言葉が少しあって、なぜか分からないなら、いちばん興奮する。
even though it's painful because then you have to spend weeks trying to fill in the blanks. - I think sometimes with some of the best stuff, I think it's more difficult obviously to be concise with something.
痛いけど。空白を埋めるのに何週間もかかる。いちばんいいもののいくつかは、短く言うのが難しい。
And I think some of the best stuff when there's a... I know I like a melody when I kind of overwrite the songs. - Overwrite?
いいもののいくつかは。メロディが好きなのは、曲を書きすぎたときだと分かる。書きすぎ？
- I'll write a bunch of verses and - There's a bunch - Of lyrics and stuff that are floating around.
バースをたくさん書く。歌詞がいろいろ浮いてる。
And then if you have all of these lyrics, then I'm like, "Oh, you take these three verses and actually if you take these lines and make them one verse
歌詞が全部あると、この3つのバースを取って、この行を一つのバースにすると、
it's actually much more powerful in what it's saying. And it's like better - Than - Explaining everything.
言ってることがずっと強くなる。全部説明するよりいい。
- I find that also it tends to be, you tend to choose the lines that just sit musically, even though you're like," I'm not entirely comfortable with the words themselves, but
僕も、音楽に座る行を選びがちだ。言葉自体には完全に安心できない。でも
it sits well. "And that's when you get that thing where you listen back to it months later going," Oh, that's why I kept it.
よく座る。何ヶ月後に聴き返して、だから残したんだ、ってなるのはそのとき。
"Because I think obviously when my laptop is full of discarded lyrics like that, and I have a corner of a fun process with Stanley Dunwood though, because
ノートパソコンは、捨てた歌詞でいっぱい。スタンリー・ドンウッドとの、楽しい過程の一角がある。
we end up using those quite a lot for other things because he's a writer.
他のことに、それをよく使う。彼は書き手だから。
So I throw all the discarded stuff at him when we're trying to do the artwork and he comes back with it and like," This is good, this is good.
アートワークのとき、捨てたものを全部投げる。戻ってきて、これはいい、これはいい、って。
"And he'll start doing jumbled collages and stuff out, which makes me see what we've been working on in a different way, which is really nice.
ごちゃまぜのコラージュを始めて、やってるものを別の見方で見せてくれる。それが本当にいい。
So it's all valid, but the stuff that ends up being in the song is kind of there despite itself. It's there because the music needs it to be there.
全部、意味がある。でも曲に残るものは、自分に反してそこにある。音楽が、そこにあることを求めてるから。
I mean, it's possible to say," No, I'm just going to put this in because I want to say this and make it work.
これを言いたいから入れる、働かせる、もできる。
"It depends on how you're singing, depends on whether it's melodic or whether it's you're talking or whatever. If you're talking, then you can say what you like.
歌い方による。メロディか、話してるか。話してるなら、好きなことを言える。
I mean, honestly, the thing I'm most jealous of, always will be, is people who can just free flow onto a mic and put it out. - I listened to a podcast that you were on.
正直、いちばん嫉妬するのは、マイクにそのまま流して出せる人。君が出てたポッドキャストを聴いた。
Oh, the podcast. It was about vocals during - COVID, I - Think. And you said something about kind of using your...
ああ、あのポッドキャスト。ボーカルの話、コロナのときだと思う。自分の、
You think of your vocal as one of the instruments in the song, and that's kind of how you tend to approach composition now. - Yeah. - Is that something that you noticed when that changed for you?
声を、曲の楽器の一つとして考えてる。今は作曲にそう近づいてる、って。うん。それが変わったとき、気づいた？
Because in it, you say you don't so much kind of sit and write a song and be like," I'm going to sit here and this is the song and this is how it
座って「ここに座って、これが曲で、こう進む」とはあまりしない、って。
goes. "Obviously, if you go back to the bends, for example, like high and dry or something, - That is like a guy with an acoustic guitar, he's singing a song.
『The Bends』に戻ると、『High and Dry』とか、アコギの人が歌を歌ってる、みたいな。
Yeah. That particular one, I wish I hadn't, but there's kind of nothing wrong with that. And it's not like I don't do it.
うん。あれは、やらなきゃよかった。でも別に間違ってはない。やらないわけでもない。
Yeah, I did this thing in Rome just introducing a film the other day and someone asked me," So what is your relationship to film music?
うん。このあいだローマで、映画の紹介をした。映画音楽との関係は？って聞かれた。
Do you see yourself just as a songwriter? "And I think that that sort of ties in with what you're saying because I don't listen to a lot of singer-songwriters.
自分をソングライターだと思ってる？ それが君の話とつながる。シンガーソングライターはあまり聴かない。
I listen to a lot of mad old folk music or I listen to film music or I listen to electronic music.
狂った古いフォークをたくさん聴く。映画音楽も、電子音楽も。
The banging away on the guitar thing is sometimes when it really speaks to me, but not a lot. And I'm not quite sure why that is.
ギターをバンバンやるのは、本当に話しかけてくるときもある。でも多くない。なぜか、よく分からない。
I think probably because we grew up when there was a real renaissance of that and the bend was that.
たぶん、育ったときに、あれの本当の復興があって、『The Bends』はそれだった。
But I think also by the time we got to Kid A, I just was excited about what else you could do with your voice, really.
でもKid Aのころには、声で他に何ができるかに興奮してた。
When Johnny and Nigel set up this thing for Kid A where Johnny's just playing the Martine and I'm just picking out random lines from my top hat that I had, and
ジョニーとナイジェルがKid Aのために組んだ。ジョニーはオンド・マルトノを弾いて、僕は帽子から適当な行を拾って、
that became the vocal. - Right. - And I'm not singing that at all. I'm literally speaking it.
それがボーカルになった。そう。全然歌ってない。文字通り話してる。
Also, I don't think it's a coincidence really also that one of my favorite singers ever is Michael Stype, who first two or three records didn't even bother writing the lyrics
偶然じゃないと思う。いちばん好きな歌手の一人がマイケル・スタイプで、最初の2、3枚は歌詞を書くことすら面倒がらず、
or rather if he did, it was like stream of consciousness. I'm not going to make this explicit. I'm the human sound in the middle of all these amazing jangling guitars and stuff.
書いたとしても、意識の流れ。はっきりさせない。すごいギターの真ん中の、人間の音だ、って。
And also, sometimes I don't like the lyrics being the point. You know what I mean?. Sometimes it's really exciting that there's just this sound. - Right. - I've got notes.
歌詞が要点じゃない方が好きなときもある。分かる？ ただ音があるのが興奮する。そう。ノートがある。
Look. - Homework. - Do you travel with a laptop? - My laptop has been dead for about six years. I don't know where the charger is. - We can help you with that.
見て。宿題。ノートパソコン、持っていく？ 6年くらい死んでる。充電器がどこか分からない。手伝えるよ。
I know. Where are your ideas? In your pocket? - On my phone. On - My - Phone. Yeah. I use Garage Band a lot and - - You should keep that to yourself, don't you?
知ってる。アイデアはどこ？ ポケット？ 電話の中。電話。うん。GarageBandをよく使う。それは秘密にしといた方がいいんじゃない？
- And voice notes. Really? I do a - Lot of - Voice notes. Yeah. Wow. Primitive of it. - No, I mean, in a way, that's good.
ボイスメモも。本当？ ボイスメモ、たくさんやる。うん。すごい。原始的だね。いや、ある意味それがいい。
I remember my mini disc, that was my best friend. - He's like, "Yes, I remember being in primary school. Yes. I also remember that." The voice note thing, I like something about it being its kind of blankest version.
ミニディスクを覚えてる。親友だった。小学校のときみたい。うん、僕も覚えてる。ボイスメモは、いちばん白紙の版が好き。
- Yeah, yeah. It's the pencil drawing. - Yeah. I think I like that. I think the thing that I try, I guess, and work towards the most, and
うん、うん。鉛筆のスケッチだ。うん。それが好きだと思う。いちばん目指してるのは、
the thing that excites me the most is when I start a record or before I've started something
いちばん興奮するのは、レコードを始めるとき、何かを始める前、
or you have a bunch of the songs for a record and I'm still kind of like, "I have no idea how this is going to end up sounding."
レコードの曲がいくつかあっても、まだ、これがどう聞こえるか全然分からない、ってとき。
- Right. - I think if there was any - I'm - Surprised - Kind of scariest version to me. - The last record is very much, it sounds like it was developed in the studio.
そう。何かがあったら。驚いてる。僕にとっていちばん怖い版。前のレコードは、すごく、スタジオで育った音だ。
- With an intention. - It doesn't sound like it comes from voice notes. - That one was less from voice notes. - Now you see. - Yeah.
意図を持って。ボイスメモから来た音じゃない。あれはボイスメモからは少なかった。ほら。うん。
I mean, there was a few. It's kind of like moments in this. There's the kind of orchestral thing or the piano songs. There's a couple of much - More - Straightforward songs.
いくつかはあった。この中の瞬間みたいに。オーケストラっぽいもの、ピアノの曲。もっとまっすぐな曲がいくつか。
And then yeah, there's probably three or four kind of moments that I think are the most down the middle like there. - So the rest are worked up in the studio?
それから、いちばん真ん中、って瞬間が3つか4つ。残りはスタジオで作り上げた？
- Yeah, it was mostly done in the studio this time. - Written in the studio. - A lot of it, yeah.
うん、今回はほとんどスタジオ。スタジオで書いた。多くは、うん。
I think it was just where I felt like I was at in my life and music that I was experiencing. I want to melt the parts of my life together.
人生と、聴いてた音楽の、その場所にいたからだと思う。人生の部分を溶かしたかった。
I'd started going out dancing a lot more and I really didn't want it to be like, "Oh, I'm listening to this music. This is kind of where I'm at."
踊りに出ることが増えてた。これが聴いてる音楽、今はここ、ってにしたくなかった。
And then I go in the studio and be like, "Well, I have to make this sort of music instead." I think it was - Really bad. I know that feeling.
スタジオに入って、代わりにこういう音楽を作らなきゃ、って。本当に嫌だった。その感じ、知ってる。
- Yeah. I think it was really like... - I know that feeling very well. - "I've just come from this place. I want that beat to keep going, or I want...
うん。本当に。その感じ、よく知ってる。さっきあの場所から来た。あのビートを続けたい。あるいは。
It was a lot about, for me, I think what I was experiencing at that time in my life. It was like I want to be on stage feeling in the middle of it like this.
多くは、そのときの人生で感じてたことだった。ステージの真ん中で、こう感じていたい、って。
And that was kind of the thing that - I - Think you did that. - Informed the record the - Most.
それが、いちばんレコードを形にした。君、それやってたと思う。
I mean, that was my favorite That's kind of my favorite part of the show where you literally do that. There was a generosity to that, which I though, yeah, that's really cool.
あれ、僕のお気に入りだった。ショーで、文字通りそれをしてるところが好き。気前があった。本当にクールだ、って。
And that is clearly someone who's discovering this thing and wants to share it in a real... So honesty of it was very cool. I was really into that.
明らかに、これを見つけて、本当に分かち合いたい人。その正直さがすごくよかった。本当にハマってた。
I mean, it's also very difficult to take that kind of music into those places. It's much easier to just make yourself totally deaf DJing in a club in Berlin and thinking that's okay.
ああいう音楽を、ああいう場所に持っていくのはすごく難しい。ベルリンのクラブでDJして、耳が完全にいかれて、それでいい、の方がずっと簡単。
And it is okay. Dance music has got a lot to offer and it's not just one thing.
それでいい。ダンスミュージックには渡せるものがたくさんある。一つじゃない。
We went through this phase when Radiohead were on tour, we had Caribou supporting us, and now I was DJing with him afterwards. It's crazy.
レディオヘッドのツアーで、カリブーが前座で、そのあと彼とDJしてた時期があった。狂ってる。
Finishing the show and then starting up at a club at one or two or even three in the morning and then it's a day off maybe the next day if you're lucky or
ショーを終えて、クラブを1時、2時、3時に始めて、次の日が休みならラッキー。
not. I know that feeling. I want this. Yeah. The reason you brought that, I was asking you like, yeah, but the new one you didn't write off voice notes, right?
そうじゃないときもある。その感じ、知ってる。これが欲しい。うん。それを出したのは、新しいのはボイスメモでは書いてないよね、って聞いてたから。
So that means then you're changing the way you write. - I mean, I've always written a lot in the studio.
だから、書き方が変わってる。スタジオでは、いつもたくさん書いてきた。
I think I tended to, what it used to be, I think was a lot of voice notes and little pieces of things or it would be a line or something and then I'd
昔は、ボイスメモや小さい断片、一行があって、
start things and then take them in and finish them there. And this was the first time it was like, oh, I'd done something at home and I'm like, oh, I think this is the song.
始めて、持っていって、そこで仕上げてた。今回は初めて、家でやって、これが曲だと思う、ってなった。
Okay. - Because now you have a studio at home. Do you work in it or you work with someone?
分かった。今は家にスタジオがある。そこで働く？ 誰かと？
- I work with - Someone - There, yeah. - I mean, I've only just got to the point now where I can turn my own studio and know where everything is.
誰かと、そこで。うん。自分のスタジオの電源を入れて、全部の場所が分かるようになったのは、やっと今。
It's taken me a long time. But once you have a place like that and yeah, it changes how you think about writing anyway because you can just endlessly mess around and then just grab one piece.
長くかかった。ああいう場所があると、書き方の考えが変わる。無限にいじれて、一つの断片を掴める。
That's it. That's what makes me want to sing that bit there. Fuck the rest of it. I'm just going to use that bit. No different than jamming around on an acoustic guitar.
それだ。あそこで歌いたくなる。残りはどうでもいい。あの断片だけ使う。アコギでジャムるのと変わらない。
It just takes up some hard disc space, that's all. But that's why I travel with a laptop.
ハードディスクを少し使うだけ。だからノートパソコンを持って旅する。
There's upsides to it and downsides to it, to be honest, because it means you've got everything at your fingertips so you can fiddle endlessly, get really excited about a synth sound and then
正直、いい面と悪い面がある。全部が手元にあるから、無限にいじれる。シンセの音に興奮して、
take it home and show it to Sam and he's like, "Okay, well there's a real synth over there. Why don't you go and use that?"
家に持ってサムに見せると、そっちに本物のシンセがある。あれを使えよ、って。
Laptops have that kind of bad habits, obsessive tendencies, which is not good, but the upside is you have all this kind of tech, you're taking everything out.
ノートパソコンには悪い癖がある。執着。それはよくない。いい面は、この機材が全部あって、全部を外に出せる。
I don't know. When we're doing Kiday, Nigel had a Pro Tools, the first Pro Tools set up because we were having to record strings. We couldn't get them on to the tape and all this sort of stuff.
Kid Aのとき、ナイジェルがPro Toolsを持ってた。最初のやつ。ストリングスを録らなきゃいけなくて、テープに入らなかった。
And I was like, "I need that because it's always a bit of a computer head." So when I saw that in the studio, I'm like, I really, I just wanted to learn it immediately.
あれが要る。僕はちょっとコンピュータ頭だから。スタジオで見て、すぐに学びたかった。
And that really changed how I though about music straight away. Suddenly I have a multi-track in my bag. I was going to ask you, where's home?
音楽の考え方が、すぐに変わった。急に、バッグに多重録音がある。家はどこ？って聞こうとしてた。
- Home? - Do you have more than one? - I think when I'm in London feels the most calm. And I'm not from here. - Where's your stuff?
家？ 一つより多い？ ロンドンにいるときがいちばん落ち着く。ここ出身じゃない。荷物はどこ？
Where's your important stuff? London. - Yeah, London. Yeah, because I've lived in my house for 12 years or something. That's the place where I feel like I really feel like been so many...
大事なものはどこ？ ロンドン。うん、ロンドン。家に12年くらい住んでる。そこが、本当に感じる場所。
I've been through so many versions of myself even in the same space in there that it's the most I feel like I really grew up in this house in a big way.
同じ空間で、自分のいろんな版を通過した。この家で、大きく育った感じがする。
I remember moving in, it was right after my 19th birthday or something. It's been through a lot of changes and things, but it's kind of the place where I'm...
引っ越したのは、19歳の誕生日のすぐあとだった。変化はたくさんあった。でもそこが、僕が。
It's like in my kitchen there is the most like, oh, this is where I live. Right. Do - You cook?
キッチンがいちばん、ここが住んでる場所だ。そう。料理はする？
I - Do. Yeah. - You're probably pretty good, aren't you? All - Right. - I'm fucking terrible. - To stay on you for a second, if I may.
する。うん。たぶん上手だろ？ まあまあ。僕はひどく下手だ。もう少し君の話でいいか。
I was curious doing this interview, for example, or the Ivas thing, for example, I think everyone communicated almost like a surprise that you were willing to be celebrated in some way.
このインタビューや、アイヴァーのことが気になった。祝われることに君が乗る、って、みんながほとんど驚いてた。
And I am curious about how your relationship with that has changed over time in terms of as someone who's so innovative
それとの関係が、時間でどう変わったか気になる。こんなに新しいことをする人として、
how much of it has always been a need to reject any sort of nostalgia to assure yourself that you're moving forward.
前に進んでるって自分に言うために、昔を拒む必要が、どれだけずっとあったか。
To me, it feels like maybe just being in a happier place to be able to realize that you can do both
僕には、もっと楽な場所にいるから、両方できるって気づけるみたいに感じる。
you can still innovate - And - Also allow people to celebrate and for you to celebrate things that you've done whether it be the Ivas or touring and playing a deep selection from your catalog
まだ新しくできて、人も祝えて、自分も祝える。アイヴァーでも、ツアーで昔の曲を深く選んで弾くことでも。
to be able to play those songs and not feel like we're living in the past right now and just be like, "We made something really beautiful I'm going to play it and that's beautiful.
あの曲を弾いて、今は過去に生きてる、って感じなくて。本当に美しいものを作った。弾く。それも美しい。
And also I cannot also still be moving forward."
そして、まだ前にも進める。
- You're right that I'm in a slightly better place nowadays, but I'd be lying that if I didn't say that something like getting a Iva Novello fellowship was not deeply confusing for me.
今は少しいい場所にいる、は正しい。でもアイヴァー・ノヴェロのフェローみたいなものは、深く混乱した、って言わなきゃ嘘になる。
I admire a lot of the people that they've given those awards to. So that's really kind of why I said, "Well, yeah, I would do that because some of these people are my heroes."
賞をもらってきた人の多くを尊敬してる。だから、やるよ、って言った。何人かはヒーローだから。
But I have a very, very strange relationship. God, this is really hard to explain. I have a very strange relationship to that element of my work. The - Navel gazing?
でもすごく変な関係がある。説明するのが本当に難しい。仕事のその部分と、すごく変な関係。自分のへそを見てる？
- No, just - - The kind of exterior. - Yeah, because I find it hard to believe in it, Which is...
いや、ただ。外側みたいな。うん。それを信じるのが難しいから。
I think the reason you talk about this moving forward thing is that the moving forward thing is that's what I believe in.
前に進む話をするのは、前に進むことが、僕が信じてることだからだと思う。
That's easy to believe in because that's new and I don't have to explain it and I don't know what I'm doing, so I'm happy.
それは信じやすい。新しいし、説明しなくていい。何をしてるか分からない。だから楽だ。
When the light is put on you and it's like, "You did this," I'm like, "Yeah, I did, but I can't tell you why, and maybe someone else can, but
ライトが当たって、君がこれをやった、ってなると、うん、やった。でもなぜかは言えない。他の誰かなら言えるかも。
I often feel in these kind of occasions, I even did after the Radiohead tour, even though it was in the middle of it, it was really fun
こういう場では、よくそう感じる。レディオヘッドのツアーのあとも。途中だったのに本当に楽しかった。
my response to it afterwards was like To crash, massively crash in terms of self-confidence. It took me months to... Well, it took me starting on my own record again two months later to go," Okay, I'm good now.
そのあと、自信が大きく崩れた。何ヶ月も。2ヶ月後に自分のレコードを始め直して、やっと、大丈夫、今はいい。
I'm fine. "Because yeah, I just have a really odd relationship with it and I've just grown used to that. To be honest, your speech that you made, his speech was great.
大丈夫。それと本当に変な関係があって、それに慣れただけ。正直、君のスピーチは最高だった。
Number one, because you came with a notebook and read it out the notebook, and number two, I was like," Yeah, man. "Just because it was really honest and personal and I could relate to it.
一つ、ノートを持ってきて、ノートから読んだから。二つ、うん、いいぞ、って。本当に正直で、自分の話で、共感できた。
Whereas when it sort of feels like a business and it feels like you're part of a business and the cameras are running, all that kind of stuff
ビジネスみたいに感じて、その一部で、カメラが回ってる、みたいなとき、
I got this legacy feeling about all of it, which I can't really explain and I probably should figure it out at some point, but I'm happy moving in and out of it.
全部に、遺産みたいな感じがする。説明できない。いつか分かった方がいい。でも出入りできて、それでいい。
- Yeah, something I'm curious about. I wonder if it's something also that maybe happens when you have children and then keep creating, because
気になることがある。子どもができて、まだ作り続けるときに起きることかもしれない。
obviously the idea of that is like you make something that continues to exist and it's not like you have children and then think I have to keep innovating so I'm done with them.
作ったものが残り続ける、って考え。子どもができて、新しくしなきゃだから、もう終わり、とは思わない。
It's almost like both a connection to the things that you do in your life and have done in your life. - Yeah, it's really important that they all integrate.
やってること、やってきたことへの、両方のつながりみたい。うん、全部が一つになるのが本当に大事。
- And can keep informing who - You - Are, but also allowing to celebrate the things that you've done as part of you're really proud of these things and people are proud of
それが、君が誰かを知らせ続けられる。やってきたことを祝うことも許す。本当に誇ってて、人も誇ってて、
those things and it becomes a different - - Well, you probably saw Agnes and Noah.
それが別のものになる。アグネスとノアを見ただろう。
They were very emotional about it and Diana, my wife was as well, and my friends, I do it for them because if they're emotional about it, I'm like, okay, that's why I'm here.
二人はすごく感情的だった。妻のダジャナも。友達も。彼らのためにやってる。彼らがそうなら、だからここにいる、って。
Because for me, I feel kind of numb about it. It doesn't make sense to me.
僕自身は、なんか感覚がない。僕には意味をなさない。
Agnes and Noah, having grown up with their dad doing this, one of the things I'm most proud of is some of the attitude that I have has rubbed off them as they grow
アグネスとノアは、父がこれをやる中で育った。いちばん誇ってるのは、僕の態度の一部が、育つうちにうつったこと。
up. I can see they have that kind of attitude to what they're doing, quite fearless about being creative and quite open and not embarrassed.
やってることに、あの態度がある。作ることにかなり恐れがなくて、開いてて、恥ずかしくない。
I mean, obviously when your kid's a teenager, they're like, "Oh God, my father's blah, blah, blah." But now it's really nice. It's a good thing. I feel super lucky about that because it wasn't easy for a long time.
ティーンのときは、父さんがどうこう、だ。今は本当にいい。いいことだ。すごくラッキーだ。長いこと、簡単じゃなかったから。
- There's kind of an option of when the thing that comes with you make something that resonates with people and then that noise and all of that and your experience becomes so existential
人と響くものを作ると、騒音がついてきて、経験がすごく「何のためだ」になる、って道がある。
of what is it for and what is this for and generally what is what we all doing here and all of that stuff. There's a version of that is kind of like, "Oh, it's all meaningless, so why bother?"
何のため、これは何のため、僕らはここで何をしてるんだ。一つの方は、全部無意味だから、なんでやる。
And then on the other side of that is it's all kind of meaningless so you can go and enjoy it a bit. - When you say meaningless, what do you mean?
反対側は、全部なんか無意味だから、少し楽しめる。無意味って、何を言ってる？
Which element meaningless? - I think general, any sort of existentialism towards meaning of life, like any sort - Of - In the work?
どの部分が？ 人生の意味みたいなもの全般。仕事の中の？
- Yeah. I think in writing about the human experience and what it means to be a human in the world and what is all of that.
うん。人間であることを書くこと、世界で人間でいる意味、その全部。
I think as someone who makes something, there's a version of sort of accepting you're not in control of it
ものを作る人として、コントロールしてない、って受け入れる方がある。
like you're saying when it happens that I think can be really terrifying to be like, "Oh, I don't control - Anything." Ah, right. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
君が言う、それが起きるとき。何もコントロールしてない。ああ、うん、うん。
- But the other side of that is actually, it can be really liberating to be like, "Oh, I'm not in control of this." You can kind of let go.
反対側は、実際すごく楽になる。これをコントロールしてない。手放せる。
And I wonder if part of that is - - Yeah, yeah. No, fair enough. You need to retain a healthy skepticism about all of it.
その一部は、と思う。うん、うん。公平だ。全部に、健全な疑いを残した方がいい。
But then I also think I would never cast it in a kind of like I'm trying to talk about the human experience at all. I would never think of it like that.
でも、人間の経験について話そうとしてる、みたいには絶対思わない。そうは枠づけない。
I think that's kind of like the art school side of me.
それは、僕の美大の側みたいだ。
By the time you've done three years of art school and you've gone through the process of explaining and watching other people trying to explain their work and get trashed for your work and
美大を3年やって、説明する過程、他の人が仕事を説明しようとするのを見て、壊されて、
all this kind of... You end up thinking that the process is the point. And that's the kind, I think me and Stanny went to the same art school and we both came out with the process being the point.
そういう全部。過程が本体だ、って思うようになる。僕とスタンリーは同じ美大で、二人とも過程が本体だ、って出てきた。
Yes, there's an end result. The real juice is the process.
うん、結果はある。本当の汁は過程だ。
The real juice is like, "I don't know what I'm doing, but in finding the things that speak to me and assembling them and presenting them and then moving on, that is my act.
本当の汁は、何をしてるか分からない。でも自分に話しかけるものを見つけて、組み立てて、出して、先に進む。それが僕の行為。
What you see and whether it speaks to you or whether I'm looking for that because I need to say something is like none of those things are linear.
君が見るもの、君に届くか、何か言いたくてそれを探してるか。どれもまっすぐじゃない。
And in order for good shit to happen, you need to believe in the process more than anything else."
いいものが起きるには、何より過程を信じる必要がある。
Kind of makes me think of some of my favorite records, you can almost hear that in the records in the way that they've been made. They were just enjoying putting this stuff together and they didn't care.
好きなレコードのいくつかを思い出す。作り方に、それが聴こえる。これを組み立てるのを楽しんでて、気にしてなかった。
Same thing as doing for lyrics and ending up using the lyrics that just mean something to you and you don't know why, right?
歌詞と同じ。自分に意味があって、なぜか分からない行を使うことになる。
The more you do it, the more liberated you become from the end result and the more liberated you become, the more you see if you're lucky
やるほど、結果から自由になる。自由になるほど、運がよければ見える。
the fact that what you do might speak to people as, yeah, you're not responsible for that In a good way. Not like, oh, I don't care because you do care, but you just want to move on.
やってることが人に届くかもしれない、ってこと。いい意味で、それに責任はない。気にしない、じゃない。気にはする。ただ先に進みたい。
I mean, the worst thing for me about OkComputer was when we finished that record, we'd been already playing those songs too much. And then when the manager said to us, "Now you're going to go on two years."
『OK Computer』でいちばん悪かったのは、終わったとき、もうあの曲を弾きすぎてたこと。マネージャーが、これから2年行く、って。
I'm like, I literally begged them, "I can't do it. I can't do it. I need to move on." Two years later, we were still going.
文字通り頼んだ。できない。できない。先に進まなきゃ。2年後も、まだ続いてた。
And that was just really fucked up because the moving on thing is like, yeah, that's not a luxury. That's entirely essential. I think everybody has their different ways of dealing with this.
本当にひどかった。先に進むのは、贅沢じゃない。どうしても必要だ。みんな、やり方は違うと思う。
Personally, I rely on the sort of thing of not doing it for too long.
個人的には、長くやりすぎないことに頼ってる。
I wish I could do it for a long time, but I can't because it sort of starts to get disconnected and a bit like, oh, I've got this move here and we do
長くできたらよかった。でもできない。切れて、ここでこの動き、ここでこの部分、になって、その場の感じがなくなる。
this bit here and it doesn't feel very spontaneous. And the whole point of a live performance is rediscovering with the people you're standing in front of something about this thing that you wrote and sharing it with them.
ライブの要点は、目の前の人と、書いたものについて何かを見つけ直して、分かち合うこと。
So that demands that you sort of... As much as a spectator as a performer, maybe that's the wrong way of putting it, but I don't think you...
だから、それを求める。見てる側でもあって、やってる側でもある。言い方が違うかも。でも。
I used to, but now I don't think you need to dig deep in order to find what you need to sing this song or whatever. I think it's the opposite.
昔はそう思ってた。今は、この曲を歌うために深く掘る必要はないと思う。逆だ。
You need to just totally let go and go, "If I'm not feeling this right now I'm good with that because maybe in 10 minutes it's going to really hit me like a train," which often it does.
完全に手放して、今これを感じてなくても、それでいい。10分後に電車みたいに来るかもしれない。よくそうなる。
- You have so many moments in your life, I think everyone does, where you have those songs, if you like music at all, where
人生には、そういう瞬間がすごく多い。音楽が好きなら、みんなそうだと思う。
you're like, "Oh, this is also a song or this is also a movie or something." I remember seeing Pulp Fiction for the first time and being like, "Oh, this is a film as well."
あ、これも曲なんだ、とか、これも映画なんだ。『パルプ・フィクション』を初めて見たとき、あ、これも映画なんだ、って。
And hearing Shine on You Crazy Diamond for the first time and being so confused by it that this was a song and that was what you could do also.
『Shine On You Crazy Diamond』を初めて聴いて、これが曲で、こういうこともできるんだ、って混乱した。
With the Carmen Police video, for example, I remember watching that and being like, "Oh, this is so brilliant." I feel like so much of your music has that weight where it really, you just remember hearing it.
『Karma Police』のビデオも、見て、これはすごい、って。君の音楽の多くには、その重さがある。聴いたことを本当に覚えてる。
It's all so different from each other in a way that is, I think, so inspiring just to see someone be so consistently great in so many different ways, but
互いにとても違って、それが刺激になる。こんなに違う形で、こんなにずっとすごい人を見ること。
in so many different ways. It can be hard to timeline it sometimes in terms of... There's not this obvious like, "Well, it was this, then it was this, then it was this, then it was this."
こんなに違う形で。順番にするのが難しいときがある。これがこう、それからこれ、が明らかじゃない。
It's all its own thing in a way that I think just makes it feel so fresh always. I've just always really been drawn to stuff like... I love Codex or True Love White or something.
全部がそれ自身で、いつも新しく感じる。ずっと惹かれてきた。『Codex』とか『True Love Waits』とかが好き。
Yeah. I just have always loved that sort of... I mean, everything in its right place is it for me. It's always been so much of that. I mean, I find it so inspiring.
うん。ずっとあの感じが好き。『Everything in Its Right Place』は、僕にとってはそれ。ずっとそう。すごく刺激になる。
- Everything's right place was my response to not being out right. We had this empty house, we had a grand piano, we had a mattress. That's the first thing I did when we moved into this house.
あれは、外に出てないことへの返事だった。空き家があって、グランドピアノがあって、マットレスがあった。この家に引っ越して最初にやったこと。
I mean, finding lost, felt lost ever since that okay can be a thing. And when I found that, okay, weirdly with that one, it was like a mantra.
迷子を見つけて、あれ以来、大丈夫であり得る、って感じた。あれは、奇妙に、唱える言葉みたいだった。
I wasn't thinking, oh, I'm writing a song. I was just really enjoying playing piano in this empty house. And I had one CD, which was a and that's it.
曲を書いてる、とは思ってなかった。空き家でピアノを弾くのを、ただ楽しんでた。CDは一枚だけ。それだけ。
And it was during the winter and there was storms all the time and just had a mattress. It was so great. Just playing this riff over and over and over again to make myself feel better.
冬で、いつも嵐で、マットレスだけ。最高だった。気分をよくするために、このリフを何度も何度も。
I love that thing of, it arrives in the post, you plug it in, you don't read the manual, you just start messing about and you find something
郵便で届いて、挿して、説明書は読まない。いじり始めて、何かを見つける、あの感じが好き。
whether it's a synth or a drum machine or guitar or anything.
シンセでも、ドラムマシンでも、ギターでも。
Establishing a relationship with this construction, this thing and responding to it and responding to what people thought you might like about it, what you don't like about it, all this stuff.
この機械、このものと関係を作る。反応する。人が好きかもしれないと思うものにも、嫌いなものにも。全部。
I've got so much out of that kind of process over the years that I figured that it must be part of what writing is, part of what our particular process is.
何年も、あの過程からすごく多くを得た。書くことの一部、僕らのやり方の一部なんだ、って分かった。
There are just some days when nothing happened and then some days you'll pick up something you're unfamiliar with and the unfamiliarity means you have to make a sort of step
何も起きない日もある。知らないものを拾う日もある。知らないから、一歩を踏み出さなきゃいけない。
you have to step across. And that stepping across means like, okay, I don't know why I like what's happening here and the I don't know why I like thing is what music should be, which
向こう側に出なきゃ。その一歩は、ここで起きてることがなぜ好きか分からない。なぜ好きか分からない、が音楽であるべきこと。
is why strangely enough, algorithms don't produce an awful lot of that.
だから奇妙に、アルゴリズムはそれをあまり生まない。
The human creativity is kind of like the same kind of thing as a scientist trying to solve a problem and he has all the things set up and he's gone
人間が作ることは、問題を解こうとする科学者と同じ種類だ。全部並べて、
he's tried everything and he can't figure it out. He's in the same kind of place, right? He's in the like, where I'm lost now, I've tried everything.
全部試して、分からない。同じ場所にいる。今は迷子だ。全部試した。
And then he goes away and he sleeps on it and he comes back and then something clicks. Because why?
それから離れて、寝て、戻ってきて、何かがカチッとなる。なぜ？
Because he's unfamiliar, because he can't make sense or something and then he can or she suddenly makes sense, something falls into place.
知らないから。意味が作れないから。それから急に意味が通る。何かがはまる。
- For me, it's just kind of where the risk falls is kind of inverted on itself of where you think it might be.
僕にとっては、リスクが落ちる場所が、思う場所と逆になってる。
Someone else might feel like trying something different feels really risky in some way or straying from what people like about your music feels like a risky thing.
違うことを試すのが怖い人もいる。人が好きなことから外れるのが怖い。
But I think the trying to recreate for that reason is that's the risky thing. - That's just awful. - That to me is the terrifying part, the idea of doing that.
でもその理由で同じものを作り直すのが、怖いことだと思う。それはただ最悪。僕にとって怖いのは、それをする考え。
And I think any time... Sometimes there's songs that we've done in the studio and you finish it and you're like, "I think this is a great song.
スタジオで曲を終えて、これはいい曲だと思う。
I think it's really good." But it doesn't excite me at all. Maybe because it has something that reminds you of something else you've done or whatever it is that it's just - I should like this.
本当にいい。でも全然興奮しない。他にやった何かを思い出させるから、とか。ただ、これは好きであるべきだ。
You're not learning anything. I should - Like this. Yeah. I - Should like this. I should like it, but you just don't. And - - I mean, I had that with Codex all the way through it.
何も学んでない。これは好きであるべき。うん。好きであるべき。好きであるべきなのに、ただ好きじゃない。『Codex』はずっとそれだった。
The rest of the band forced me personally to finish it. Everyone was like, "You're fucking crazy, man." I'm like, "All right. So sometimes..."
バンドの残りが、僕に仕上げさせた。みんな、狂ってるぞ、って。分かった。ときどき。
- For me, at least so much of the studio experience of making something is almost trying to block out the fact that anyone's going to listen to it for a second to just
僕にとっては、何かを作るスタジオの多くは、誰かが聴く、って事実を一瞬でも閉め出そうとすること。
make what - It is. You're doing it for you. - Yeah. You have to just be making what do I want to listen to at this time in my life?
それであるものを作る。自分のためにやってる。うん。今の人生で、自分が聴きたいものを作らなきゃ。
What is it that I feel like I want to do, say, make? And the fact that people are going to hear it feels like that happens late.
やりたい、言いたい、作りたいと感じるものは何？ 人が聴く、って事実は、あとで起きる感じ。
The realization of that feels like it happens later. And I think the live playing music to an audience is the part where you're embracing the fact that people listen to it and that it's connected with people.
その気づきは、あと。ライブで人にやるのは、人が聴いて、人とつながった、ってことを受け入れる部分。
And I think for me, the kind of emotion that happened at the end of the London shows was like...
ロンドンのショーの終わりに来た感情は、僕には。
I think it was just a realization of that those shows felt so much to me like a culmination of so many people's support, I think. I think that's the bit.
すごく多くの人の支えが、一つに集まったみたいに感じた。そこだと思う。
That part feels so external. I think you make the thing, and then how many shows you play is determined by how many people want to come see it.
その部分は、すごく外にある。ものを作る。何本やるかは、見に来たい人の数で決まる。
And I think what - Was - Turns out a - Lot. What was emotional for me was it felt... I was kind of realizing, I think, how deep it is and how deeper it is
結果、たくさんだった。僕にとって感情的だったのは、気づいてたんだと思う。どれだけ深いか。
how much deeper it is than kind of any one moment or one song or any sort of fluke thing.
一つの瞬間や、一曲や、まぐれより、どれだけ深いか。
It just felt like supported kind of in a way more than like, "We're here because we want to hear this song that you've done
支えられてる感じだった。この曲を聴きたいから来た、より、
or we're here because we like when you used to play that one, or it just felt like we're here because we believe in what you're doing." And I think that's what it felt like to me.
昔あの曲をやってたのが好きだから、より、やってることを信じてるから来てる、感じ。僕にはそう感じた。
And I think that's why I found it so emotional was I think... - Also, you have to give a lot of yourself. You have to give a lot of yourself, and that makes you very open.
だから感情的だった。あと、自分をたくさん渡さなきゃいけない。たくさん渡す。それでとても開く。
I've heard people say to me, "Careful with that, because you're exposed to all these people and all this kind of thing." And like, "Yeah, it doesn't bother me.
気をつけろ、こんな人たち、こんなものに晒される、って言われた。うん、気にならない。
Did, it did. It did. Used to. It doesn't bother me anymore." - I mean, I think if you're sensitive enough to want to write, sensitive enough to be aware of the part of you that wants to say anything
昔は気になった。昔は。もう気にならない。書くほど敏感なら、何かを言いたい部分に気づくほど敏感なら、
if you're sensitive enough to care enough about a song to be like, "It's not right yet.
曲を気にするほど敏感なら、まだ正しくない、って。
I have this idea and I want it to be right and I want it to be great," there's a sensitivity there that needs it to be great.
このアイデアがあって、正しくしたい。すごくしたい。そこには、すごくある必要がある繊細さがある。
And I think if you're sensitive enough to do that, to feel it and then to communicate it and then see it through put so much of your life into making sure this synth sound is correct
それを感じるほど敏感なら、伝えて、最後まで見て、このシンセの音が正しいように人生の多くを入れるなら、
then I think you're sensitive enough to feel when those moments land on you in what might come back at you.
その瞬間が自分に着地するとき、返ってくるものを感じるほど、敏感だと思う。
I think a lot of the time when you're making stuff, you're kind of trying to reject what's coming back at you to remain sort of beginner's mind of how do I go back
ものを作ってるとき、多くは、返ってくるものを拒もうとしてる。初めての気持ちを残すために。
to before anyone liked this song that I did or anything like that. You're always trying to get back to a sense of starting again.
この曲が好きになる前に戻るには、って。いつも、また始める感じに戻ろうとしてる。
So I think those moments where you kind of let go and open up and allow it all to come in and you get to feel that
だから手放して、開いて、全部を入れさせて、それを感じる瞬間は、
I think it is a wave of something that you don't live with every day. So it's quite - Like - You certainly don't, bro.
毎日一緒にいない波だと思う。だからかなり。君は確かに、そうじゃないよ。
I guess if I was going to answer that I'd say when we did the first radio show in Madrid, we had to do this thing where we had to walk through the audience.
それに答えるなら、マドリードで最初のラジオのショーをしたとき、客の中を歩かなきゃいけなかった。
Never done that before. Walk through the audience and we had to stand on the stage getting prepped before we went up, up.
やったことがなかった。客の中を歩いて、上がる前にステージで準備した。
The first time we did that after, I don't know how many years, all of us, the whole band were like, "Okay, keep it together. Keep it together."
何年かぶりにそれをやったあと、全員が、大丈夫、持ちこたえて、って。
Because I just wanted to... I already wanted to burst into tears because I hadn't been exposed to whatever that was for so long and to walk through the middle of it and then I never forget it.
もう泣き出したかった。あんなに長く、あれに触れてなかった。真ん中を歩いて、忘れない。
I mean, all of us, we were like, "Holy shit. Holy shit." Also, you mentioned Beginner's Mind. Do you know the book?
全員、なんてことだ、なんてことだ、って。初心の心にも触れた。あの本、知ってる？
- Yeah. - The Suzuki book. Okay, good. Very important. - Very important. Which brings us back to walking the artist's perspective where we began. There's the bow, there's the seal.
うん。鈴木の本。分かった、いい。すごく大事。すごく大事。それで、始めたところに戻る。歩くこと、アーティストの視点。お辞儀があって、締めがある。